<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daniel&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Daniel&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 00:52:04 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dfamonteiro.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Formula 1&#39;s cost cap could be improved: here&#39;s how</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/cost-cap-f1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 00:52:04 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/cost-cap-f1/</guid>
      <description>The introduction of the cost cap in Formula 1 has allowed teams to do something they aren&amp;rsquo;t exactly well known to do: turning a profit. F1 teams suddenly had a business case that made sense for the first time since the inception of the sport and instantly saw their valuations skyrocket. It has also meant that the bigger F1 outfits have had to downsize to fit the cost cap, which led to a couple of interesting side effects1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can Formula E race at Macau?</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/macau_gen3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 19:33:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/macau_gen3/</guid>
      <description>When it comes to historical races, the Monaco Grand Prix is definitely an odd one. Older than Formula 1 itself, it is F1&amp;rsquo;s most glamorous and most prestigious race on the calendar, featuring a track layout that remains largely unchanged1 since the race&amp;rsquo;s inception in 1929. Unfortunately, when it comes to on-track action, it is an absolutely dreadful race, with cars that are impossible to race on this track. So, when Formula E announced that the full track layout would be used for the 2021 Monaco E-Prix, people were hopeful that the premier electric series would provide a good race in this historical venue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How soon can a driver clinch the title: a nuanced analysis</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/championship-title-math/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2021 21:40:37 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/championship-title-math/</guid>
      <description>The 2020 Formula 1 championship was one of the most uncompetitive seasons in recent history. Facing an underpowered Ferrari1 and a RedBull plagued with rear instability problems, Mercedes in some people&amp;rsquo;s eyes had already won the title2 before even turning a wheel in a free practice session. Lewis Hamilton, however, did need to beat his teammate Valttery Bottas in order to win the driver&amp;rsquo;s championship, but anyone who watches F1 knows that Hamilton is simply on another level, compared to Bottas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing an intermediate representation of Brainfuck using Rust</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/brainfuck-ir/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 23:11:53 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/brainfuck-ir/</guid>
      <description>Brainfuck is an interesting programming language, to say the least. As the most prominent Esoteric programming language out there, it provides a truly cursed programming experience. It is quite minimalistic as well, featuring only 8 distinct instructions and a programming model that can be best described as a glorified Turing machine, making writing a Brainfuck compiler an interesting programming exercise. However, we might as well go a step further and develop an intermediate representation for it, because, well, why not?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 13:13:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a third year software engineering student at FEUP (Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto).
I am currently interested in multithreaded programming, rocket control, orbital dynamics and in analysing mega constellations as distributed systems. As a fan of Formula 1 and Formula E, I enjoy analysing certain aspects of those championships and imagining what the future of motorsport will look like, on a technical level.
In my spare time, besides writing code, I enjoy playing games such as Kerbal Space Program, Factorio and blundering queens in chess.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
