<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daniel&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Daniel&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 23:42:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://dfamonteiro.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Solving the mathematics of Factorio Quality: Pure Recycler Loop</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/factorio-pure-recycler-loop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 23:42:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/factorio-pure-recycler-loop/</guid>
      <description>The pure recycler loop is the simplest possible way to grind for legendary items, making it the logical next step of our quality analysis journey. Armed with the knowledge we gained from the previous post of this series, we&amp;rsquo;re going to calculate the efficiency of this quality grinding method and do some statistical analysis of how the production of quality items is affected by the quality chance of the recyclers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving the mathematics of Factorio Quality: The Fundamentals</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/factorio-quality-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 13:52:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/factorio-quality-1/</guid>
      <description>Prologue&#xD;Link to heading&#xD;Video games have this incredible ability to evoque certain feelings and states of mind on the people that play them. You can experience pretty much every emotion, starting from happiness, amazement, and wonder going all the way to sadness, frustation, and heartbreak. Games can make you laugh and cry, they can make you focus, and sometimes they make you think.&#xA;Factorio is a game that makes you think.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving the Jindosh Riddle with constraint programming</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/jindosh-riddle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 21:38:40 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/jindosh-riddle/</guid>
      <description>I was playing Dishonored II, when I came across a locked door. In order to make progress in the game, I had to open this door. When you get close to it, you begin to realise that there is more to this door than it first meets the eye:&#xA;The Jindosh Riddle door lock&#xD;There is no key that opens this door. Instead, you have 5 slots with names and 5 slots with objects which need to have the right values to unlock the door.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applying clustering techniques to the F1 2024 schedule for fun and profit</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/f1-clustering/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2024 02:26:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/f1-clustering/</guid>
      <description>I was finishing my Formula 1 Cornering Performance Breakdown project when I came up with the idea of using the existing code infrastructure to generate cornering data for every track on the 2024 calendar. As part of that project, I tagged every corner with a tag highlighting how fast that corner is. With that information, I can determine how much time is spent on each type of corner. The remainder of the time in lap, which isn’t spent negotiating a corner, is the time the drivers spend at full throttle on a lap, tagged below as STRAIGHT.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Formula 1 ATR rules have to account for dominance</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/f1-atr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 22:00:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/f1-atr/</guid>
      <description>Dominance is a common occurrence in Formula 1. While most other forms of motorsport have made efforts to limit the amount of design freedom that teams have (to save costs), F1 and MotoGP swim against the current and remain the only premier competitions where pretty much everything is bespoke1. This leads to the creation of incredible works of engineering in the form of the fastest racing bikes and cars on this planet.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formula 1&#39;s cost cap could be improved: here&#39;s how</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/cost-cap-f1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 00:52:04 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/cost-cap-f1/</guid>
      <description>The introduction of the cost cap in Formula 1 has allowed teams to do something they aren&amp;rsquo;t exactly well known to do: turning a profit. F1 teams suddenly had a business case that made sense for the first time since the inception of the sport and instantly saw their valuations skyrocket. It has also meant that the bigger F1 outfits have had to downsize to fit the cost cap, which led to a couple of interesting side effects1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Formula E race at Macau?</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/macau_gen3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 19:33:17 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/macau_gen3/</guid>
      <description>When it comes to historical races, the Monaco Grand Prix is definitely an odd one. Older than Formula 1 itself, it is F1&amp;rsquo;s most glamorous and most prestigious race on the calendar, featuring a track layout that remains largely unchanged1 since the race&amp;rsquo;s inception in 1929. Unfortunately, when it comes to on-track action, it is an absolutely dreadful race, with cars that are impossible to race on this track. So, when Formula E announced that the full track layout would be used for the 2021 Monaco E-Prix, people were hopeful that the premier electric series would provide a good race in this historical venue.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How soon can a driver clinch the title: a nuanced analysis</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/championship-title-math/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2021 21:40:37 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/championship-title-math/</guid>
      <description>The 2020 Formula 1 championship was one of the most uncompetitive seasons in recent history. Facing an underpowered Ferrari1 and a RedBull plagued with rear instability problems, Mercedes in some people&amp;rsquo;s eyes had already won the title2 before even turning a wheel in a free practice session. Lewis Hamilton, however, did need to beat his teammate Valttery Bottas in order to win the driver&amp;rsquo;s championship, but anyone who watches F1 knows that Hamilton is simply on another level, compared to Bottas.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Developing an intermediate representation of Brainfuck using Rust</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/brainfuck-ir/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 23:11:53 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/brainfuck-ir/</guid>
      <description>Brainfuck is an interesting programming language, to say the least. As the most prominent Esoteric programming language out there, it provides a truly cursed programming experience. It is quite minimalistic as well, featuring only 8 distinct instructions and a programming model that can be best described as a glorified Turing machine, making writing a Brainfuck compiler an interesting programming exercise. However, we might as well go a step further and develop an intermediate representation for it, because, well, why not?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 13:13:52 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a software engineer with a MSc in Informatics and Computer Engineering @FEUP (Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto). I am currently working at Critical Manufacturing.&#xA;I am currently interested in multithreaded programming, rocket control, orbital dynamics and in analysing mega constellations as distributed systems. As a fan of motorsport (F1, MotoGP, WEC, etc), I enjoy analysing certain aspects of those championships and imagining what the future of motorsport will look like, on a technical level.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
