<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>maths on Daniel&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/tags/maths/</link>
    <description>Recent content in maths on Daniel&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 19:33:17 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dfamonteiro.com/tags/maths/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Can Formula E race at Macau?</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/macau_gen3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 19:33:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/macau_gen3/</guid>
      <description>When it comes to historical races, the Monaco Grand Prix is definitely an odd one. Older than Formula 1 itself, it is F1&amp;rsquo;s most glamorous and most prestigious race on the calendar, featuring a track layout that remains largely unchanged1 since the race&amp;rsquo;s inception in 1929. Unfortunately, when it comes to on-track action, it is an absolutely dreadful race, with cars that are impossible to race on this track. So, when Formula E announced that the full track layout would be used for the 2021 Monaco E-Prix, people were hopeful that the premier electric series would provide a good race in this historical venue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How soon can a driver clinch the title: a nuanced analysis</title>
      <link>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/championship-title-math/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2021 21:40:37 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dfamonteiro.com/posts/championship-title-math/</guid>
      <description>The 2020 Formula 1 championship was one of the most uncompetitive seasons in recent history. Facing an underpowered Ferrari1 and a RedBull plagued with rear instability problems, Mercedes in some people&amp;rsquo;s eyes had already won the title2 before even turning a wheel in a free practice session. Lewis Hamilton, however, did need to beat his teammate Valttery Bottas in order to win the driver&amp;rsquo;s championship, but anyone who watches F1 knows that Hamilton is simply on another level, compared to Bottas.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
